[Music]
so
good evening good day everyone great to
see you all
uh so welcome to episode 24 and before
we begin
a big thank you to all of you for
helping this channel cross
go beyond 100 000 subscribers one lakh
subscribers
it's all thanks to you i have seen uh
lots of messages of congratulations so
thank you so much to everyone i'm sorry
i can't respond to each of
each one of you individually but it's
all thanks to you uh we are doing great
work together
and uh this this channel is not about me
it's about you
which is why until now i have been
taking your questions and answering
these questions
throughout these past 23 episodes
and now that i have a good understanding
of what you people want to know then
in the future soon i'm gonna start
making more detailed and more elaborate
videos
about those topics so this is all all
about you
it's about what you need to see what you
want to see and what you want to
hear about so once again thank you so
much to everyone
for supporting my work
and for being together in this in this
project
and thank you again for those of you who
have become members i really appreciate
that
memberships are open in case you weren't
aware so thank you to all of those
all of all of you who have supported me
in that fashion
thank you very much so we talk about
science and physics
and technology and ai today
so i know that the most popular topic
on this channel is history i know that
but we have to understand that
one of the major lessons of history is
that
science and technology is critical in
taking any nation any civilization
forward
if you are not proficient in science and
technology if you don't have the
scientific attitude and approach then
you basically can't progress
so that is why science and technology is
very important we all need to
understand what it is we need to all
develop a scientific outlook
and that's why this session is also
very important so let's get into it
with question number one
so kunal asks why did the us government
stop the apollo program after 1972
and why are they not resuming it now
since technically they are more advanced
now
so the space program the apollo program
all of that was part of the great space
race
of the 20th century it is a
technological competition that took
place between the united states and the
erstwhile ussr
and the ussr where the first uh
was the first nation to take a big
stride in this matter by sending the
first satellite
the first artificial satellite into
orbit i think it was in 1957
sputnik one and they were also the first
uh
country to send a human being into earth
orbit
which was yuri gagarin and the first
woman valentina tereshkova
etc so the soviets took the first big
strides
in space exploration and the americans
were scared they were really
paranoid about this they've worried that
these soviets could put
nukes in orbit and they could spy upon
the americans from just 100
kilometers overhead so that's why the
americans decided to
take this on in a massive manner that's
why they also launched their
own space program eventually they
surpassed the
achievements of the ussr and one of the
major achievements was the
apollo program the in which they sent
several
manned missions to the moon uh you first
had
unmanned missions then you had manned
missions one the first mission
manned mission was simply an orbital
mission it went round the moon and came
back
and then you had lunar landings the
first person was neil armstrong etc
so the real purpose of this was to
achieve first
parity with the ussr and then to surpass
the technological achievements of the
ussr
and there's always a military background
to any space program there's always a
military under current
so that is the reason why they also were
afraid that the ussr could
set up bases on the moon and claim the
whole territory of the moon for
themselves
that's why they embarked upon this
program because the
soviets also had plans to send humans to
the moon
so these two nations were neck and neck
throughout
most of the 20th century second half of
the 20th century
it was a race for not just technological
supremacy but
military supremacy and
once the americans uh went far ahead of
the ussr especially in the moon program
that's when it became apparent that the
soviets were most likely
not going to uh take them their own moon
program further
and that's why the americans did not see
any point in continuing with that
further
beyond the 197 between beyond the early
1970s
and that's why the last moon landing was
in the 1970s after which they never
tried to go back until now
now what's going on is that there is a
new moon race there's a
new moon rush we know that the moon is
is rich in various resources various
minerals there is a great deal of water
there
and there is this uh there is helium 10
in
in abundance in the lunar soil in the
regolith of the moon
and this is a very promising future
nuclear fuel so this is one of the major
reasons why
the chinese are going back to the moon
the americans are planning to send human
beings back to the moon even india is
involved
to some extent in this moon race we were
supposed to land
the chandrayaan lander
on the moon's surface near the south
pole a couple of years ago
did not exactly work out as we planned
so we chandrayaan three program
iii mission is supposed to happen
sometime in the coming future
let's see when it is so the americans
are definitely going back to the moon in
a very very serious manner this time
there is a concerted rush to go back to
the moon
the chinese currently are ahead of the
us in terms of
the number of landers they are sending
to the moon especially on the far side
of the moon
there is uh there's at least one mission
operational right now
a chinese mission at least one so the
americans are sending people to the moon
in
in the next two or three years back to
the moon
so that's what the status is right now
there is going
this is we are we are at the cusp we are
at the beginning of a
new rush to the moon and the new space
race because now the technology
has advanced a great deal from the 1970s
and now we can actually start exploiting
humanity can now actually start
exploiting space
and its resources in a commercial manner
so we're gonna see the privatization of
space uh
elon musk and jeff bezos are
competing for supremacy in space right
now spacex is ahead but uh
blue origin is not very far behind so
and so that's what's going on
we can we may soon start to see the
privatization of space too
so it's it's essential that india gets
involved in a big way in this
i hope that some plants hopefully are
afoot
okay what's my view what is my view on
the panspermia theory what is panspermia
panspermia is the idea that uh
that space that life basically
originates in space itself
it is the hypothesis that microscopic
life is present in large quantities in
interstellar space in in basically on
space
dust on comets on asteroids
and and life can even be transmitted
through spacecraft microscopic life if
you have microorganisms that humans
because we know that there are
microorganism organisms on our skin
now if we are constructing a spacecraft
it will be handled
with human hands right and then if we
send it to the moon
or to mars those microbes those
microorganisms from
earth will end up on mars so there is
another means by which
uh microorganisms can go across
planets so this can happen through
spacecraft it is believed that
this according to this hypothesis it is
believed that such
microscopic life occurs across the
universe across galaxies
and we know that there are certain
microorganisms on the earth such as
tardigrades for example the so-called
water bears that are almost
indestructible they can survive the
vacuum of space
and therefore there could be other such
organisms as well extremophiles
so this is the hypothesis panspermia
that
life actually is seeded through these uh
through either cometary impacts or
asteroid impacts or just via space dust
and maybe the seeds for life these
microscopic seeds for life they may
occur across the universe
so it is a hypothesis it hasn't been
proved but
well it's certainly a viable hypothesis
because we do find
uh evidence of of
organic hydrocarbons complex organic
hydrocarbons even amino acids
on on meteors on meteorites
and if you look at the spectral
composition of comets you you see that
there is
uh carbon chemistry there as well
so it is definitely a viable hypothesis
there is no proof for it thus far but
it's definitely possible we've even
found
a mars rock that seems to contain
fossilized microorganisms it's not been
proven conclusively but
it does look tantalizingly like
the fossilized remains of a
microorganism of bacterium of some kind
so it's definitely possible that space
rocks from mars could have reached the
earth
in the early phase of the solar system
and if there was life on mars it could
have been
uh transferred to the earth and maybe
there was life even before our solar
system
came into existence and that was
present in the uh building blocks
of our solar system so these are all
possibilities there is no proof thus far
but it's definitely a viable theory
and maybe the maybe our dna came from
somewhere else
even that is a possibility so so it's a
hypothesis it's not been proven but it's
definitely scientifically
valid so as of today we don't have any
evidence for it
but we are searching for it if we
actually find some microorganisms
on a comet or an asteroid or elsewhere
then it would definitely bolster this
hypothesis and make it
more likely or more probable
okay what happens to the matters the
contents of a neutron star after it gets
after it collides and gets destroyed
with another neutron star
because as we know uh matter is neither
created nor destroyed yes
you're right there is conservation of
mass and energy in the universe
so what happens when two neutron stars
collide so it depends on the total mass
of these two neutron stars first of all
these are extraordinarily compact
objects you have the mass of the entire
sun
within a diameter of about 10 kilometers
so that's extraordinarily compact these
are the
most these are the densest objects in
the universe apart from black holes so
that's what newton's stars
are now the maximum neutron star
mass is defined by the tallman
oppenheimer vocal limit which says that
a neutron star has between 1.5 to about
three solar masses
i think the average or the
yeah approximately the average it's not
a very definite limit
but the uh it seems that the upper limit
is up to three
most likely 2.2 or 2.3 solar masses
and beyond that if a neutron star gets
has more mass than that
then it becomes a black hole so when two
neutron stars collide first of all
there's going to be a cataclysmic
collision
and a great deal of energy will be
radiated out in the form of
gravitational waves and light
and some matter will be ejected out of
this collision
so what happens where is that a great
deal of heavy elements are created
when two neutron stars collide for
example
in a large star more than
25 times the solar mass you have these
core collapse supernovas
and this supernova happens when the star
starts trying to fuse
iron at its core and iron is basically
nuclear ash you can't fuse iron stars
cannot fuse iron
and that's why they undergo these
supernovas so the heaviest element that
a star
can create is essentially iron
but we know that there is there are
heavier elements in the universe you
have
gold for example you have uranium
and various other heavier elements so
how are these elements
synthesized and the answer is they are
synthesized in neutron star neutron star
collisions
so these neutron star neutron star
collisions throughout a lot of ejecta
and debris and these are in the form of
extremely heavy elements like gold and
uranium and
and thorium and other elements so that's
what happens
but the resultant neutron star
that is formed after the collision it
is it a neutron star is it something
else that's a question and that depends
on this
limit the tormant or openheim or vocal
limit so if the resultant
object has a mass of greater than
around three solar masses then it
becomes a black hole otherwise it
becomes a larger neutron star
so that is what happens when two neutron
stars
collide now that's a very energetic
collision and it produces an
intense flash of radiation in various
uh frequencies and spectra if it happens
near the earth it will blind you
basically
that's how energetic the light output is
so that in short is what happens
during and after a neutron star neutron
star collision
akash asks is there any difference
between the big bang
theory and the cosmic inflation
theory that's an interesting question so
one second here we go let me share a
screen
okay so this here is essentially the
timeline of the universe
so what is the big bang theory it is not
a theory
of the origin of the universe it is
essentially a model of the history of
the universe
it starts with a big bang we don't know
what caused the big bang
but it's about what happened after the
big bang right
so according to this theory and this is
the best theory that we have thus far
it is the most detailed theory that we
have and it explains a lot about the
universe
so it's our best theory thus far so
according to this theory in the
beginning you had
the big bang this initial singularity
which is a point of infinite density and
and
mass energy and it expanded it was not
an explosion it was an expansion
and about 10 raised to minus 34 or 35
or thereabouts seconds
after the initial expansion you had
something called
inflation so this was super luminal
inflation
and it lasted it basically it lasted
just about 10 raised to minus 36 or 35
seconds
and the universe expanded by a factor of
about 10 raised to 26 times
so that is a ridiculous humongous amount
of inflation
in such a short incredibly incredibly
short period of time
and that is what gives the universe the
properties that it has today
homogeneity isotropy etc
flatness and all that so cosmic
inflation
is essentially part of the big bang
theory right
it is the very initial almost the very
initial phase
of the universe's history that we
actually understand we don't really know
we don't understand the
the physics of the very early universe
before this cosmic inflation actually
happened
we know there were quantum fluctuations
that got dispersed
out into space and you had most likely
primordial
microscopic black holes produced in
abundance before inflation
and even after inflation and these most
likely formed the seeds
of galaxies the seeds of the
supermassive black holes that you have
at the center of galaxies
and all that so that is all part of the
big bang theory
and cosmic inflation is also part of the
big bang theory it's part of big bang
cosmology right and this inflation is
supposed to
uh been triggered off by a hypothetical
field called the inflaton
and so that in brief is about inflation
or
cosmic inflation which is very much part
of the big bang
model of cosmology which is the best
theory that we have
thus far so this is one uh
and this is another example another way
of looking at the
history of the universe in the beginning
at zero seconds you have the big bang
and before 10 raised to minus 32 seconds
elapsed
the universe has undergone this massive
spurt of inflation
in which it ex it enlarges it becomes
larger by 10 raised to 26 or 27 times
which is incredible and before inflation
you had quantum fluctuations which got
dispersed all over
and then you have these different uh
phases uh you have
nuclear synthesis you have protons
nuclear synthesis etc
and eventually you end up with the
universe that we have today
uh the first light is at around 380 000
years after
the initial expansion of the universe
this is
the big bang expansion and so on so this
is
how this is the best theory the best
model of the history of the universe
that we have
as of today and inflate it all starts
after the big bang
with cosmic inflation and this expansion
of the universe is still going on but at
a much
slower rate so i hope that answers the
question
okay shri ganesh asks so this is about
uh something i had said in in an earlier
episode
about the fact that isro is so so badly
underfunded we have the best scientists
in the world
the most talented people in the world
and yet isro is not really
basically it's not developing any new
technology right now it's not developing
reusable rockets it's not developing
boosters that can come back
and return to earth on their own it's
not building heavier rockets
it not it's not looking into light sail
technology
i mean it's just like a commercial
enterprise which
launches satellites for various
governments and private companies for a
fee and that's all it does
it's the pslv in the g and the gslv
and the reason for this is that there is
no ambition on the part of the political
dispensation of india
politicians have no um scientific
ambition apparently because we don't see
any sign of it
and that's why they're not funding
israel enough so that it can develop
more newer technologies larger more
powerful rockets etc
for example if you want to send a
mission to the moon
you can't send a rocket that goes
straight to the moon you have to lift
that
uh spacecraft into orbit and then you
have to do
a number of orbit raising maneuvers it
takes
months to reach the moon if you had a
powerful and enough rocket you could
reach the moon in
what two three days less than a week for
sure so that's the kind of
uh limitations isro is hamstrung with
it's all about
funding and there's not enough funding
to do all all
this right so the question is if the
government is unwilling to fund isro
can the people isro fund isro how can we
fund isro directly
etc so here's the point
let's say we start a crowdfunding
campaign
all of us together uh let's say we all
donate
a thousand rupees each and if it is one
lakh of us
so that's 10 lakhs is one crore so you
may have a hundred crores
right no 100 lakhs is one is one crore
so if each of us raises uh donates a
thousand rupees
you we may be able to raise 10 crore
rupees well
and even if it's not just one lakh of us
even if it's one crore of us
each giving one thousand rupees we can
raise 100 crore rupees
for israel now how do we fund israel
with that money
we're gonna have to hand that money over
to the administrators and bureaucrats
who oversee and control the budget of
israel
right and then it's all in their hands
it's not like the government of india
doesn't have money they have the money
but all these scientific projects and
programs in india
are all run by
bureaucrats who know nothing about
science and who don't really care about
anything except bureaucracy
right so this budget will be
i mean the allocation will be decided by
the bureaucrats and they may even shift
the money elsewhere because they may
decide that israel doesn't really need
that sort of money and all the projects
have to be sanctioned by the bureaucrats
who govern isro or drdo or anything
right
so the real problem is not the
scientists the scientists are
not in charge of the budget they don't
have the power to decide the budget they
don't have the power
it is the bureaucrats and the higher-ups
in the government to decide all these
budgets and decide the allocation
of funds and all that so even if we
raise some kind of money
and hand it over to the government for
israel
eventually it's going to go into the
hands of these bureaucrats and that
my friends is the real problem in the
governance of india the bureaucrats
i am not saying they're all bad people
there are many nice people as well okay
there are many patriotic people even in
the bureaucracy
ias etc and yet
the system is built in such a manner
that even if you are one patriotic
person
you cannot do anything except what the
system tells you
if you if you try and go against the
system you can't be transferred 15 times
in 10 years
and you're gonna end up doing nothing so
that is the problem in india
we are stuck with this colonial era
system
and the governments throughout the
decades have done
absolutely zero to try and reform the
system
so today we have this young energetic
nation we have teenagers we have 20 year
olds
and all of them all of you guys want to
see
massive change you want to see massive
progress you want to see
the nation unleashed the energy
unleashed
and it is these colonial systems that
are holding you back
the entire government is is designed
like this
the moment you try to interface with the
government the moment you approach any
government
organization or or organ you know how it
feels
it's like time has stopped
so that is the system that is what
we need to see change so even if we
raise money for israel it's going to end
up in the hands of the bureaucrats and
then god alone knows what happens with
it
unfortunately that is where we are today
70 plus years after independence
it's still like we are in 1947
unfortunately
okay how do doctors assume
the amount of memory loss in case there
is a memory loss somewhere
and also how like memory is stored as
jpegs or gifs how is human memory stored
what an interesting question so when
a doctor a neurologist etc
says that there is says that a
particular individual or person
is suffering from memory loss they
cannot quantify the memory loss
neuroscience is a very very uh
very imprecise science
right it's it's very vague it's a lot of
voodoo and hand waving to it
you can't determine first of all we
don't understand the brain
we don't understand how it works we have
a rough
understanding of what goes on in which
part of the brain little bit you know
but it's very very rudimentary or
understanding and
we don't know where human memory is
stored precisely
if i see something new today where are
those associations
stored within the brain in what form are
they stored
we know that it's most likely the
associations between different neurons
that cause the uh
the storage of memory but how do we
recollect smells and sounds and things
like that
in such vivid detail in some cases
right and and where does consciousness
emerge from
certain scientists tell you that
consciousness and emotions are all
chemical reactions that go in the brain
but they are unable to
give even a basic fundamental theory of
how it happens
so the brain is a enormous mystery
the consciousness is an enormous mystery
how is memory stored we don't know for
example in jpegs or gif files these are
static files
so the memory is stored in a static
manner you can
basically see it in terms of zeros and
ones if you have
have the software for that
in the human mind there are no zeros and
ones it's very very different it's very
complex
so we don't know how memory is stored
it's probably the associations between
the trillions of neurons
and dendrites and all that between in
the human brain that that
probably causes the storage of memory
but we don't know how
so neuroscience psychology psychiatry
these are very very
well there's a lot of there's a lot of
pseudoscience in there there's a lot of
hand waving and voodoo in there
there is very little real understanding
of how things happen
yeah sure neuroscientists are able to
basically operate on the brain and
maybe rectify some problems remove
tumors etc
and yet there's a lot it's like it's
like dark matter and dark energy
we understand five percent of the
universe and we don't understand 95
of the universe it's all unknown to us
similarly
the human psyche the human mind the
human brain consciousness all that it's
also
most of it is basically completely
unknown to us we don't know how it works
so that's where we are at in science
this this thing
right on top of our eyes on our heads
that itself we don't really understand
how it works
it is the most complex
object that we know of in the entire
universe and it's
a vast mystery
the moon is moving away from the earth
at about an inch
every year does it prove the fact that
human life on earth will disappear when
the move will
moon will have no impact on earth and
menstrual cycles of women on earth will
stop
as a result humanity will end i've been
asking this
for the three live sessions okay
so this solar system is about 4.6
billion years old the earth moon system
is roughly four and a half billion years
old
so when the earth moon system was formed
it is hypothesized that there was a
giant
impact of another planet on the earth
and the material that was ejected out
into orbit went into orbit around the
earth it coalesced
in the form of the moon and there is
some evidence that
supports this theory so when the moon
was
first formed it was much closer to the
earth than it was than it is today
in fact the length of the day on the
earth
the rotation period was about four or
five hours
and the period of the moon around the
earth
was also four or five hours and then
it's been receding away from the earth
at a certain speed at a certain rate
right now it's about
two and a half or about three
centimeters per second
it's the rate at which human nails grow
so at this rate it's going to take
billions of years
for the moon to recede
any significant distance away from the
earth now
the history of humanity is about
a billion a million or two million years
in age that's how old humanity is
i think the human chimpanzee split
happened about two million years ago
and even those humans that split off
from the chimpanzees
were very ancient humans archaic humans
the earliest known evidence of modern
humans
modern anatomically modern homo sapiens
is about 250 000 years
well 250 000 years or even 2 million
years
is an eye blink of time in the
cosmological
scale of of in the in the yeah in the
cosmological scale
it's nothing so even in the next two
million years
the moon will have no will not have
receded any significant distance away
from the earth to have any real change
to have any real effect
on the way the world functions
the earth's moon system functions and
the question is
will humanity last another 2 million
years 2 million that's 20 lakh
will it last that long or will we leave
this planet and go away somewhere else
so these are questions right so the time
scales that we are talking about are so
vast that that humanity is too small
to even envisage that we have been
around for two million years at most
right some people believe that uh indian
history is eight lakh years old or 30
lakh years old or whatever
so that is the kind of thinking that we
need to address
so that's a different topic but you know
it's it's it's in a way similar to this
this uh uh idea we are we are
contemplating right now
so the time it will take for the moon to
move away a significant distance and
change the the amount of time the the
length of the day on the earth etc is
gonna be in the scale in
in the realm of tens or hundreds of
millions of years
so it is not perceptible to humanity and
therefore it's not going to make any
difference
by the time humanity will also have
evolved a great deal
if it is still around that long on this
planet
right and by the time the moon reaches
the furthest
distance away from earth it's going to
be another 50 billion years or so
by which time the sun won't even exist
so therefore these questions are i mean
the time scales that we are talking
about are too
vast to even worry about or or take
or take seriously because it's too long
it's longer than the current age of the
universe right
so that's it it really doesn't matter
for us
okay akash asks what is the oort cloud
okay a why does it exist b how
big is it c does it exist around every
solar system
and the could it have helped in evolving
life in our solar system so let me give
you a visual
exam visual idea of what the wood cloud
is let me
share an image
okay this is a
rough model of the solar system so
here if you can see my mouse pointer
it's the sun
here is the earth so this distance
between the sun and the earth is called
one astronomical unit
so this is this graph is on the
logarithmic scale
so this is one astronomical unit this is
another 10 astronomical units 10
so this is the distance between the uh
the sun and the set in and saturn
this is a hundred astronomical units
that's where the voyager one spacecraft
is
roughly around right now so that is
basically
where the solar system ends that's the
beginning of interstellar space
and the oot cloud is a hypothetical
spherical cloud of basically uh
ic objects that are the nuclei of
future comets so that is
what the old cloud is it is an enormous
cloud let me show you a different image
okay so let's take a look at this so if
you look at
this image here the
red orbit here is that of mars the green
one is earth
this diffuse orbit over here is the
asteroid belt
and the orange orbit here is the orbit
of jupiter
if you look at it here it's very small
the orbit of jupiter and the purple one
is the orbit of pluto
and you have the caper belt over here
and this red
dot is the minor planet called
cedna which is currently around 90
astronomical units from the sun one
astronomical unit is the earth sun
distance
here you have the orbit of sedna which
is an enormously elongated
orbit yeah so it tells you how small the
orbit of pluto is
in comparison let me remove that right
so that
gives you an idea of the orbit of sedna
and this is the orbit of sedna in
comparison with the
old cloud so that gives you
an idea of how large
the old cloud is and how far away it is
from us it's essentially in
interstellar space but it is still under
the influence of the sun's
gravity it's an enormous cloud
hypothetical enormous cloud of
cometary uh nuclei the nuclei of comets
now what happens is that if this root
cloud does exist and there is
a good chance that it does exist so if
this
oort cloud does exist then it is only
loosely
influenced by the sun's gravity because
it is so far away from the sun
it's essentially in interstellar space
and it is also
affected by the gravitational attraction
of nearby stars passing stars
and also the gravitational attraction of
the milky way itself
and therefore you see that from time to
time various
cometary nuclei get dislodged from their
orbits
and the some of them are sent tumbling
towards the sun
and that's what eventually becomes
comets
so this is basically a hypothetical
reservoir
of comets so it's almost halfway to the
nearest star
that's what the old cloud is so it's
hypothetical but there's a very good
chance that it does exist
and it exists because of the way the
the early solar system formed the solar
system formed
from a primordial cloud of gas that was
left behind from the death of another
star
so the solar system is a reincarnation
of a previous solar system
and the material that was left behind
after the circumstellar disk
coalesced into the sun and the planets
that became the old cloud
initially it was supposed to be it is
believed that it was much closer to the
sun
and eventually it drifted out further
further away from the solar system from
the sun
because of the gravitational
interactions of the gas giant planets
okay so it's quite far now it's in
interstellar space
it's very very large but it's very
diffuse
does it exist around every solar system
there's a good chance that it exists
around many uh stellar systems
we haven't really seen because it's it's
such a small diffuse
it's not small it's very large but it's
very diffuse and the
cometary nuclei they're in are very very
small
so it's almost impossible to detect
around
other stars and even around our own
solar system
which is why it's still hypothetical but
if it exists
around our solar system there's a good
chance it exists around other solar
systems as well
could it have helped in evolving life in
our solar system well
we spoke about panspermia this theory
that
uh micros microscopic life exists
across the galaxy on dust grains and
comets and asteroids etc so if some of
these
uh cometary nuclei did contain the seeds
of life
then it could have seeded life on the
earth in the very early
solar system when the earth was under
intense bombardment
from comets and asteroids so there is a
possibility
that it may have played a role in the
uh seeding of life
in the early earth
akriti asks uh which
way to look at gravity is more profound
is
einstein's way in which space-time
foreign fabric is a four-dimensional
thing or is it the exchange particle
concept of gravitons which one is
correct
correct well uh we know that general
relativity which looks upon space-time
is a four-dimensional fabric
it is a stage upon which or within which
the universe
plays out so that definitely uh it is
the best
theory of gravitation that we have as of
today it is a very accurate theory
it uh all of its predictions thus far
have been proven to be correct
and it is being tested all the time and
it is the most accurate theory that we
have thus far
so einstein's view the space the
four-dimensional space-time fabric is
definitely correct but it is not
completely correct because we know that
there are certain
uh certain scales at which it breaks
down for example we are unable to
quantize
curved space time for dimensional space
time we are unable to do it
quantum field theory is not compatible
with
general relativity and we have these
singularities that this theory throws up
in the form of what happens within
the hypothetical black holes space and
time
the curvature becomes infinite the mass
energy density also becomes infinite
this is an indication that the theory
breaks down at the quantum level at the
ultra microscopic level
so there's definitely a better theory
out there somewhere we still haven't
figured it out
and the one of the ways we are looking
to do this is to quantize gravity
to have a quantum theory of gravity in
which the hypothetical graviton
will be the mediator of this
of this force it will be the exchange
particle
let me share the this this image
so this is the standard model of physics
this is the best theory of particle
physics that we have the best theory
that describes the
five percent of the universe that we can
actually see
so you have these uh three generation
generations of matter
the quarks the leptons and the gorge
bosons you have six quarks you have
the leptons electron muon tau lepton and
the
corresponding neutrinos then you have
the gluon which is the exchange particle
for the strong nuclear force you have
the photon
which does it for electromagnetism and
you have the wnz bosons that are the
gauge bosons for the weak nuclear force
and then you have the higgs boson
that imparts mass to various particles
and which is responsible for the
mass of the universe now if the graviton
concept is correct then you would have
one more 18th particle here
which would be the graviton which would
be the gauge boson
for the quantum theory of gravitation
for for quantum gravity well thus far we
have seen
uh no evidence that this actually is
correct
the the graviton is a hypothetical spin
zero particle
boson so this thus far has not been
proven
it is far from being proven so the best
theory that we have as of today
is einstein's general relativity
four dimensional space time but there
could be a better theory out there and
that's what we are seeking
so maybe gravitons do exist but we are
very far from
seeing any experimental evidence of
gravitons and very far from formulating
a proper theory
a coherent consistent theory of quantum
gravity
sujit asks can you please tell us about
the newly found
third type of supernova you have been
asking many questions from the past
three sessions
i hope you are okay so here we are the
what is the
so let's first talk about the first two
types of supernova
there's the type one supernova and the
type two supernova
so let's talk about type 2 first which
is strange but let's talk about that
first
so the type 2 supernova is when you have
a star
so first let's talk about our own sun
will our own sun go supernova
it won't it is too small to
to undergo a supernova explosion so our
sun
basically contains about 73 percent
hydrogen 25
helium and then some other trace trace
traces of other heavier elements and the
nuclear
energy i mean the nuclear reaction
within the sun is the fusion of hydrogen
into helium
so that is what drives the the but that
is what
drives the sun now after the hydrogen is
used up most of it the sun will fuse
helium into a heavier element
and the sun doesn't have enough mass to
fuse heavier elements than this
so once the hydrogen and helium fuel is
used up the sun will become a red
supergiant
and eventually the outer layers will fly
off into outer space
and what will be left behind will be a
white dwarf and that will be the end of
the sun's
existence as a star that's how it will
slowly cool down
now when you have a star that is between
10 to 25
solar masses it is able to
fuse heavier and heavier elements so it
keeps it goes on fusing heavier elements
to to create energy
fusion energy until it reaches the
element of
iron and iron basically to fuse iron it
takes more energy than the
the fusion reaction is able to give out
so iron is basically nuclear ash
and once a star a star starts creating
iron in its core its lifetime can be
measured in milliseconds
so once the iron is formed in the core
of a star which is between 10 to 25
solar masses
it within a fraction of a second
its energy output seizes and this
entirety of the star
all the outer layers enormous outer
layers that are being
pushed out and held up by this by the
energy of the fusion reaction
they all collapse onto the core of the
star
and they collapse onto the core of the
star and then they bounce out and that
is a supernova explosion
and what's left behind at the core is a
neutron star
so this is called a type 2 supernova
if a star is heavier than 25 solar
masses
you won't have a neutron star which will
form at the center it'll be a black hole
now if you have a star now what is a
type one supernova
a type one supernova is a strange
supernova in which you have a large star
and a neutron star that uh and a white
dwarf
and the white dwarf that are that are
orbiting each other so it's a binary
star system
two stars a regular star and a white
dwarf
so let me show you what this looks like
hang on
let me make this yeah here you are so
you have a regular star here if you can
see the image
and it it has a companion star which is
a white dwarf a small one
and in this system the white dwarf star
is stealing material from its companion
star
okay so this is the that type of this is
that that type of system
a binary system two stars in which the
white dwarf is stealing material slowly
slowly
from its companion star now there is
something called the chandrashekhar
limit
which is 1.4 solar masses which is
as big as a white dwarf can get now this
white dwarf is stealing material from
its companion star so it's getting
larger
once it reaches the chandrasekhar limit
and exceeds the limit
it essentially vaporizes in in an
enormous explosion
and that is called a type 1 or type 1a
supernova
it's also called a standard candle
because we know exactly how much
luminosity it will have
so this is a type 1 supernova a white
dwarf detonates and destroys its
companion star
in the process that's a type 1 supernova
now we have a third type of supernova
which has been hypothesized but it seems
to have been discovered recently
so this is a star which is between 8 to
solar masses now a star is basically
when it is it is uh so it is basically
held up by electron degeneracy pressure
which is a quantum effect
in which electrons don't want to be too
close together so they push against
uh the star the star's exterior
and that's what holds the star into this
in in this shape
now when certain uh nuclear reactions
happen
so basically i'll tell you about quantum
degeneracy what it is
all the matter that we see it is able to
have a certain shape because of quantum
degeneracy pressure
so that is a quantum effect which gives
the universe and the world that we see
the shape it is it's what makes matter
solid
it is not electrostatic repulsion it is
quantum degeneracy pressure
that that gives solidity to matter
so it is a quantum effect that we
actually see in real life even though we
don't realize it
so this electron degeneracy pressure
basically pushes back against the outer
layers of the star which want to fall
back inside
but in this type of star between 8 and
10 solar masses
at a certain stage what you have is that
you have electron capture a nuclear
reaction that starts happening
in which certain heavy elements start
capturing electrons
and these electrons fuse with protons
and produce neutrons
so suddenly this electron degeneracy
pressure which is
holding the star up it vanishes and the
star
implodes and then explodes so there is a
third type
of supernova that has recently most
likely been discovered
it's called an electron capture
supernova
so it seems that we have finally
detected
this type of supernova we i'm not sure
what is left behind at the end of this
thing
is a white dwarf left behind is
something else left behind i think it's
still a matter of conjecture
but this is what it is the type three
supernova
and electron capture supernova
does the revolution of our solar system
around the milky way
have any effect on the earth's
atmosphere or life
that's an interesting question so uh the
solar system the sun
does revolve around the center of our
galaxy the milky way
so one such revolution is can be looked
upon as a galactic
year a galactic year and one galactic
year
is about 230 million years
so every 230 million years the sun makes
one revolution
around the center of our galaxy that's
one galactic year
so by that uh measure the sun is about
20 galactic years old
it's quite young so
does it have any effect on the earth's
atmosphere and life
not really not not to any extent that we
can measure
because the galaxy that the the
neighborhood of the galaxy that we live
in
it also revolves in that manner around
the galactic center so it doesn't really
have
much of an effect on our solar system
the amount of gravity that we feel from
our parent galaxy is the same the
stellar neighborhood and other stars
around us are more or less the same
so it doesn't really affect us to any uh
significant or measurable extent it's
just one measure of the lifespan of a
star
so from where the sun is it takes about
galactic years it's it's about 20
galactic years old
with that measure in mind
rajwal asks can a person having no
technical background
enter in the field of ai artificial
intelligence
is programming and coding essential for
ai
what can be a roadmap for a beginner
having no no thick
background to make a career in ai see in
any scientific field
you need to know math and so math
is the mathematics is the foundation of
all sciences
unless you want to go into biology or
something which is basically
a soft science in any hard science like
physics
physics or chemistry or computer science
you going to need mathematics
and you will need to be quite good at
mathematics so that is the price for
entry
that is the price you have to pay to
enter into this field the first thing is
mathematics so you need to
learn basically differential equations
linear algebra and all that which would
need you to first learn algebra geometry
college level calculus and then move
further ahead depending on how deep you
want to go into it
so there's a definite learning curve
into this you know
and secondly you need to learn
programming coding
it is a prerequisite for for doing any
significant work
in the field of machine learning or
artificial intelligence
neural networks any of that so first you
need to
learn mathematics if you want to do real
research in ai and secondly
even if you don't really learn
mathematics that well you need to know
coding
programming that is a prerequisite that
is an it is non-negotiable
without that you just can't do anything
in eia so that's what i would suggest
if what is a roadmap well start learning
math you can learn math online
for free and start learning a
programming language i think one of the
best programming languages out there
for any beginner is python you can learn
it entirely for free
if you have a computer or laptop you can
check out various courses on youtube or
other places
where you can learn the whole thing in
great detail for completely free
and you can download free tools that
will that will allow you to
start doing the coding and all that so
you can learn everything for free today
so i would suggest you should do that if
you're really interested in this
aryan asks what does the statement i
need to
add x dimensions to make my theory work
mean
and secondly in one episode of the
runway show
i heard you say that all the technology
we use today is based on quantum
mechanics can you explain
how so what does it mean when you say
that i need to add
more dimensions x dimensions to make my
theory work so let's say
you have a theory you're trying to see
more patterns in this theory
so for example there is something called
kalooza client theory in which
you are able to see more patterns if you
uh
if you add one extra dimension in space
so that mathematics becomes different
every physical theory every theory in
physics
is a mathematical theory it's all
constructed using mathematics
and it's so so you assume three
dimensions
and you play all the mathematical
equations you see how they evolve and
what they give you
and that is a mathematical three theory
in three dimensions
now you can add an extra dimension to
this theory and see how how it looks
so kalutsak line theory is a theory in
four dimensions that shows us more
more patterns or symmetries
between for example gravity and
electromagnetism
and when you when it comes to string
theory in which they try to construct a
theory of the universe
a model of the universe built upon
the existence of one dimensional strings
then they find that
three or four dimensions simply do not
give you the
the uh the super symmetries that you see
that we see in space time and all that
so mathematically they are forced to add
either six or seven dimensions
to this theory in order to get a
coherent mathematical theory of the
universe
so if you add six dimensions you end up
with ten total dimensions
in addition to space and time and if you
add seven dimensions to it you end up
with an
11 dimensional string theory so string
theory is basically uh
well it's not a theory it's a hypothesis
because it doesn't really give you any
testable predictions thus far
but that's what it is so it's basically
you're trying to gain the mathematics
and try to see if it
throws out any theory that actually
makes sense in the physical world in the
physical domain
so essentially you are tweaking the math
by adding or subtracting dimensions and
seeing
what fits best so that's what it means
roughly tentatively
by saying that i need to add extra
dimensions to my theory to make it work
okay second the second part of the
question
i said that most of the technology we
use today is based on quantum mechanics
yeah can i explain how
that's a good question so we don't
realize it but
almost everything that we use today is
based on quantum quantum
technology on the practical uses of
quantum mechanics
for example transistors and microchips
and microconductors they are all based
on quantum mechanical effects
microprocessors usb drives solid state
drives
the sensors that you have in smartphone
cameras and dslr cameras
all of these are based on quantum
mechanical effects
which means that computers won't work
without quantum mechanics and
smartphones won't work without the
without quantum mechanics and quantum
technologies which essentially
essentially tells us that the entire
computer and smartphone industry
is dependent on technologies that are
based in
quantum mechanical effects then you have
lasers and leds and fiber optics
so fiber optics are basically classical
uh
these are classical objects these are
long fibers
through which laser pulses are passed
and that is again all about quantum
mechanics
so these are governed by the laws of
quantum mechanics so the entire
telecommunications industry
base is based upon quantum mechanics we
would not be having this conversation
right now
this telecast right now if uh fiber
optic technology did not you
did not exist and that is based on
quantum mechanics
so this what we are doing right now
would be impossible
if we had not discovered quantum
mechanics and if we had not learned how
to use that in technology
right so making phone calls is because
of
quantum mechanics scanning groceries in
a supermarket
you have these laser scanners that's
again quantum mechanics
then you have gps
so gps when your phone picks up a gps
signal and tells you where where you are
how does it happen
you have all these you have this
constellation of satellites
in space these gps satellites these
satellites
they're basically transmitting a very
accurate
uh transmission of the time
they have these atomic clocks on them
each of these satellites
these atomic clocks are very accurate
counters of time it is based on the
transition between quantum states
of either cesium or rubidium atoms so
your phone basically
gets a signal of the time what time it
is from a number of different satellites
gps satellites and it does some
mathematical calculations how much time
it took
for the signal to come from which
satellite and based on that it's able to
triangulate
your location on the planet so it's all
possible because of the
quantum transitions between rubidium and
cesium atoms that these atomic clocks
measure and then transmit via the
satellite
so that's again quantum technology then
you have electron microscopes you have
magnetic resonance imaging or nmr
imaging nuclear magnetic resonance
which is based on quantum spin you have
ped scans
position emission thermography which is
again a quantum effect
so i could go on and on but as you can
see
all of these technologies this entire
vast bouquet of technologies
that we take for granted today they are
all
based upon quantum mechanical effects if
we had not discovered quantum mechanics
if we had not developed the technologies
based upon this
theory then none of this would have been
possible
so that's what i meant by saying that
almost all the technology we use today
is based upon quantum mechanics
okay akash asks what is plasma
how does it look and feel like as the
sun is made of plasma correlated to this
does the sun have a surface where we can
hypothetically stand
and what about the gas giants so plasma
can be considered to be the fourth state
of matter
you have solid state liquid state and
gas state
plasma is a fourth state so what is a
plasma plasma also is a gas
but it is a ionized and charged gas
so you have a gas in which the gas
molecules have been stripped of their
electrons
so these are ionized molecules or
ionized
atoms whatever raised right and so you
have a gas
of these charged particles ions and free
electrons so that's what the gas is made
of
so in in the case of the sun you have
mostly
hydrogen and helium so the solar plasma
is made up of
protons which are hydrogen nuclei alpha
particles which are uh helium nuclei
and free electrons so that is the solar
plasma
so that is what plasma is it is
basically a ionized gas
base made up of ions and free electrons
it is electrically conductive
right it conducts electricity it is very
strongly affected by magnetism so you
can create plasmas on the earth plasma
tvs etc
are they use this technology of of
creating plasma
now when it comes to the sun does the
sun have a surface the sun has layers
the overall density of the sun is
greater than the density of water
so if you would place the sun in a
hypothetical ocean made of
water the sun would sink below it
because the sun is denser than water
now when you come closer to the sun's
core
you get densities that are in excess of
100 times
the density of water which is basically
much denser than the human body
so yeah if you were to if you could
withstand the heat of the sun and you
were to plunge into the atmosphere of
the sun
eventually you will reach a place where
the sun's density is greater than your
density so you will just float there
right because of buoyancy so there
you'll reach a place
a layer in the sun where you would just
float up and down up and down bob up and
down
so it's not a surface it's a layer a
level in the sun
where the density exceeds the density of
the human body if
the human body can ever withstand that
sort of temperature right
and the you could say the same about gas
giants so for example jupiter
its outer atmosphere is is just gas as
you go
towards the core towards the center of
jupiter the
density of the gas
of this planet starts increasing it goes
on increasing even the temperature goes
on increasing it gets really hot inside
and a certain depth below the below the
surface
of jupiter you will reach a density
where the density exceeds that of the
human body
and therefore you will just float there
or bob there
so that's about jupiter or saturn as
well or uranus or neptune they all have
increasing density as you go towards the
interior
so i hope that answers this question
excuse me one second
okay divyansh asks
can you talk about the trappist-1
exoplanet which is said to be in the
habitable zone
how do we decide whether planet is in
the habitable zone
from here does being in the habitable
zone
imply the existence of life in that
region
okay what is the trappist exo
system so the trappist-1 uh
star is a red dwarf star
it's about 40 light years from where we
are from the sun
from the earth it's a very small
red giant star its diameter is just
slightly larger than the diameter of
jupiter
but its mass is significantly more than
that of jupiter which is why it is a
star that which is why there's a fusion
reaction
going on inside it it's a very small
star it's a very cool star compared to
the sun or other stars and it's a dim
star
now what is the habitable zone the
habitable zone
is the region around a star
where liquid water can exist
so it's neither too close to the star
where water would evaporate
nor is it two it is too far from the
star where water would freeze
it is that region around a star where
water can exist
in as a liquid so it depends on from
star to star some stars are very hot so
it would have been
the habitable zone would be further away
some stars are cooler
than the habitable zone is closer so in
the case of the trappist-1 planet a
star it would be much closer than what
it is
in our solar system so the earth and
venus and and mars most likely are
within the habitable zone
in our solar system because this is the
region where
liquid water can exist so there
i think there are about seven exoplanets
that have been discovered around the
trappist one star
and i think these are terrestrial type
planets rocky planets
and i believe there are at least three
of these exoplanets
that are in the habitable zone around
this star
and at least one seems to be very
earth-like which
would indicate perhaps that there is a
possibility of a liquid ocean on it
which could indicate a chemistry that is
similar to that of the earth so maybe
there is life there maybe
so being in the habitable zone does not
imply or guarantee the existence of life
it just says that there could be life
there similar to the kind of life that
you find
on the earth so the trappist-1 system is
very interesting because you have so
many
earth-like planets there and also
because you have at least three planets
that are in the habitable zone so there
is a
possibility that there could be
earth-like conditions there
on at least one of these planets and
maybe there could even be
the possibility of some form of life
there so it's very interesting
okay why can't can't we engineers make
india's own google
with the help of great professors in
iits
and students collaboration i am thinking
about it i'm glad that you are thinking
about this
well how do you make a google first of
all you need a good idea you need a good
you need all the infrastructure you need
you need to
a good idea is not enough you need
investments
you need funds you need angel investors
to
recognize the fact that you have a good
idea and then they need to
invest in you and in your work and give
you the
means and the funds and the and the
resources needed to take your idea
to the next level that's how google was
that's how google was built
two students came up with this idea of
semantic search
and then they took it forward and they
were desperately short of cash
they needed cash for for building an
array of computers that could hold
all this data and they needed a lot of
funds for that and they
got lucky that angel investors invested
in them
and they kept on getting more
investments and that's how this
giant company was founded that was the
genesis of the company that eventually
became this global giant
in india we don't have the angel
investment ecosystem
right we don't have a silicon valley
kind of place where there will be so
many investors
and there'll be all this uh all these
engineers
who can interact with each other and get
ideas from each other
and all that and in india the laws and
the system is such that it is
very non-conducive to entrepreneurship
the moment you become you start
doing good there'll be all kinds of
extra
fees that you will have to pay to
various
politicians etc any entrepreneur knows
this in this country
convenience fees or whatever you call
them you know
so the entire system is basically
set up against entrepreneurship that's
why you have all these
companies like flipkart etc that are
based outside of india
they operate in india but they are based
out of india because they do not want
to be to be subjected to all these
problems that entrepreneurs and
companies face in india and that's why
india simply doesn't develop right
because
we have all the talent but the system is
is loaded against
any company like that succeeding when it
comes to the iits
well who told you there are great
professors in the iit's i'm not saying
they're all bad professors
maybe 10 of the professors in the iit
are good
or great but i would not say that
most of the professors in the iits are
great all right
and look at the way the iits are
go to any iit okay you will find that
there are crores of rupees of
investments in the iits
in the auditoriums and in the washrooms
you have one crore ruby washrooms very
well
built you know very luxurious even the
auditoriums are very luxurious
but when you go to the lab you will see
that the equipment is at least 20 30
years old
it's obsolete
so the people who are running the iits
and managing the budgets and the funds
they are funding auditoriums and
washrooms and all that
and they are not funding the technology
they are not allowing the iits to have
the latest
cutting edge technology everything is 20
to 30 years old
and the attitude of most of the
professors
well it's like they don't want any
progress unfortunately
i have to say this i think anybody who
has tried to do research
or a phd in any iit knows this this is
what they all
face so it's it's basically we are
breeding mediocrity over there
in all the iits to the greatest extent
there are definitely some shining stars
among the professors
but those are few and far between
overall
you have the reservation system which is
basically the opposite
of meritocracy you may get less marks in
the entrance exam but because of
reservations
and all of that you are still given
admission to the iits and all
and the same goes for the appointments
of professors and all that
so what the iits once were
maybe 15 years ago has been destroyed
the iits were once in the top 10 around
the world
in technical institutions and and
research institutions in science
and technology today they are nowhere in
the top 100 even
so the quality in the iit is terrible
most of the professors are mediocre
the equipment is obsolete and the people
who are funding and running the iits
have the wrong ideas they are
they are constructing million dollar
washrooms and million dollar auditoriums
and neglecting the actual purpose
that the iits were built for
or meant for and the students you will
see the most of them are basically they
are just trying to get a degree and get
the hell out of india
because there's no future here because
of the the system is
so that is a state of affairs in the
iits
uh and overall in the indian education
system
nothing is being done to redress this
basically we need to revamp the
education system
from the ground up making some small
changes cause
cosmetic changes here and there and this
new academic reform that was
that was that was instituted last year
it's all a joke
it's it's pointless it's worthless so
what is needed in india is
the kind of education reforms that were
done in china 30 years ago
it's still going on china basically
turned their entire education system
around especially
in the science and r d field they
completely revamped their education
system
and that's why china is now beginning to
lead the world when it comes to ai
and quantum computing and
superconducting
computing and everything else
so we don't have great professors in the
iits to the most part
the students basically they want to
leave i mean i don't understand why
can't the iits
take the lead in for example in building
supercomputers
india doesn't india has maybe two or
three supercomputers in the top 100
supercomputers in the world
why can't you have an annual competition
in the iits between all the iits
of making of constructing the most
powerful super
computer why can't we do that and give
the team that wins
a 10 million dollar prize they can use
it as seed funding for
starting a new venture why can't this
sort of initiative be taken up
why can't you have this sort of
competition among the iits between the
iits every year
india will leapfrog all the other
nations within
within just a few years if you have this
sort of innovation happening in the iits
unfortunately there is no uh initiative
like this
in the iit's the professors the
administrators nobody cares
so this is the reason why india is not
doing well in science
in technology the system is built is
designed
in a manner that hampers
any such progress the system rewards
mediocrity
and that is what needs to change i am
very positive about india
india has the best talent in the world
and we are seeding the world with our
talent
we are exporting our best talent abroad
and they are
the ones who are heading microsoft and
google and whatnot today right
so what if we just we were able to build
a system
in india that actually values this
talent and rewards this talent
india would immediately not immediately
within a decade within a generation
india would become a superpower
so that is the job of the government we
can keep wishing we can keep saying but
we
don't have the power to change anything
we are not in charge of the
administration of the iit's or the
education system
we are not in charge of the budgets
everything is in the hands of the
government it is for them
to wake up from their slumber and
make some reforms do some reforms
quickly
aditya asks will the evolution of ai
lead to millions of jobless
people good question
so ai will definitely eliminate lots of
jobs ai
is all about automation it's about
efficiency
so automation will eliminate lots of
manual jobs and this is definitely going
to affect the
lesser developed countries the most
you can already see some some of these
effects in india the
emergence of these big online retailers
like amazon and flipkart
are cutting into the profits and the
wages of these small
shops the small kirana shops and all to
a very great extent
right so it's already happening but when
when
ai becomes comes into real effect
in full force it's going to eliminate
lots of jobs
lots of manual jobs and all so yeah so
it's problematic in when you have a
system that is capitalistic in nature
where you will be paid only if you have
a job
the dream of science fiction writers in
this 50s and 60s and 70s
was that with the advent of superior
technology
the need to work will be eliminated and
the technology and the robots will do
the job
work for us and human beings will be
able to live
live a life of leisure
but the dystopian
uh scenario we are facing today is that
the capitalistic system
is predicated upon making people work
and if you don't work you have no income
if your job is eliminated by ai then you
become jobless then you become
basically you have no income so you'll
be you go below the poverty line and you
have to depend on other people
and you become a burden on society that
is not the way it would be that's why
this
this system uh which comes from the west
is
is a very well it's not the right system
for the world i am not advocating
communism or marxism or socialism
we need a different system in which
people don't need to work a certain
hours of day
in order certain hours per day in order
to get a certain wage
one of the uh solutions people are
giving is ubi universal basic income
well that is one possibility we need to
come up with better solutions but as of
today
with the increasing emergence of
technology
and the increasing ubiquity of
technology in our daily lives
and because of artificial intelligence
machine learning automation all that
you will definitely see millions of job
losses
especially in less technologically
advanced societies
such as india in africa you will see
a lot of stress on these societies going
forward
so that is something the government
needs to start thinking very seriously
about
and doing something about
paras asks what do you think about the
con concept of super determinism
that everything that happens in the
universe is predetermined
interesting question so
in physics in in the laws of physics
if you know the state of a system at a
certain
initial time
then you can determine this the state of
the system at a future time
you can determine how the system evolves
over time
at every step of the way until a future
time or it
until any time in the future so the laws
of physics are deterministic
if you know the initial conditions you
can calculate
the future conditions maybe 10 seconds
down the line maybe 3000 seconds down
the line
maybe 10 million years down the line you
can calculate
if you have enough computing power
now when the big bang happened
when the initial singularity expanded
and gave birth to the universe that we
are in today you had a set of initial
conditions
there was a very large number of
variables but with a
large enough computer you can actually
calculate the initial conditions
and you can actually calculate the
future conditions at any given point in
time in the future
maybe 13.8 billion years later so if you
have a powerful enough computer
given the initial conditions of the big
bang you calculate
and compute where the universe would be
precisely 13.8 billion years later
so this would indicate that everything
that's happening in the universe was
predetermined
at the time the universe was born which
would in which would indicate that what
we are doing right now
was all predetermined which would
indicate there is no free will
that everything that we think that we
are thinking or we are making choices
is actually been predetermined at the
birth of the universe
so this theory is called super
determinism
it is a theory there's no proof for it
maybe there can be no proof of it
but it is one of the theories that
resolves the paradoxes of quantum
mechanics
because we are told that quantum
mechanics is extremely strange
it is counterintuitive you have spooky
action at a distance
you know quantum entanglement all that
but
if super determinism is true then all of
these problems go away
all the randomness also goes away so it
is one of the
possible solutions to the paradoxes
and inconsistencies of quantum mechanics
so basically it says that everything is
based upon
differential equations and whatever
quantum randomness
exists or occurs in the world is purely
statistically random
there is no free will in it we cannot
will that randomness into existence
so if this theory is correct it means
that we are main
the universe is a clockwork universe and
even we
are simply clockwork components of it
and everything we are doing
and will do in the future has already
been predetermined
in the past so it's one of the
interesting
and somewhat scary theories in physics
harsh asks how exactly does
gravitational lensing work
is there a way for humans to recreate
that effect with our technological means
in the future
or does it just happen at vast galactic
scales
so gravitational lensing is the bending
of light
because of matter in general relativity
in the four-dimensional fabric of
space-time
the uh force that we perceive as gravity
is
basically the curvature of space-time
and space-time gets curved because of
the presence of
mass so when space-time is curved
because of mass then a light beam
can't pass straight through space-time
it also becomes
curved so this is one of the predictions
of general relativity
that matter bends the path of
light and that is how we basically
proved it
the general theory is indeed correct for
example let me show you an image
so this here is a galaxy it's an image
of a galaxy
that has been curved and warped by the
presence of
mass between us and that galaxy
so this circular thing is called an
einstein ring
it is a single object that has been
distorted
and warped because the light coming from
it
has to pass through this mass central
mass so it becomes bent
and that's what that's what causes the
distortion in the image
there's another way of looking at it
it's a black hole passing between us
and a galaxy we have the viewer there is
a galaxy
over there and there's a black hole that
comes between us and the galaxy
and that's how it distorts the light
coming from the galaxy
so basically this is gravitational
lensing
we can observe it at vast galactic
scales
we can also observe it during a solar
eclipse when stars
which are actually physically behind the
sun become visible
during a solar eclipse because the light
is bent around the sun
so that is gravitational lensing it is
very it is
with the current technology that we have
we can't really produce the effect
but we can see it there is no technology
for gravitational lensing it's just that
mass will bend the path of light so
that's all it is
there is no real technological
application of it
thus far
okay aditi asks what is the speed of
gravity at the event horizon of a black
hole
that's an interesting question so
gravity has only one speed
and the speed at which gravitational
effects propagate
in the universe is the speed of light
which is the cosmic limit
in the universe so think about it this
way
what if the sun were to suddenly
disappear which means it goes dark
well we will not know this sitting here
on the earth
for at least eight minutes because the
time it takes for light to
from the sun to reach the earth is about
eight minutes and a little bit more
so if the sun were to go dark we will
come to know only eight minutes later
and similarly the gravitational effect
of the disappearing of the sun would be
apparent only eight minutes later so the
speed of gravity
across the universe is the speed of
light that is the speed at which
gravitational effects
or the ripples in space time propagate
so the speed of gravity is the same
wherever you are whether it's at the
edge of the event horizon of a black
hole or at any distance
away from a black hole the speed of the
speed of
the gravitational effects is the same
everywhere
it's the speed of light
all right my friends i am done with the
pre-selected questions let me see some
live questions
some live questions and a thank you for
all that
thank you to all the new members thank
you very much
jatin asks photon has wave as well as
particle nature
wave particle duality so how does it
travel in space where there is no medium
as particles need medium to travel
well photons
are localized concentrations
of energy in the universal
electromagnetic field so the entire
universe
is permeated with fields that is quantum
field theory there is no such thing as
empty space there is no thing is vacuum
space is teaming with
space is permeated with fields
so one of these fields is the
electromagnetic field and these photons
are local concentrations of energy or
local waves
in this infinite electromagnetic field
so you have this medium in vacuum
this electromagnetic field it's
everywhere
and that's what photons are
manifestations
of off so photons basically travel in
space
in vacuum particles can travel in vacuum
definitely
so that's what it is i hope that answers
your question they can be particles as
well as waves
uh they are localized wave packets so
they are like particles yes
and you can actually feel the radiation
pressure that's what
uh creates the that's what is behind the
light sail technology so the impact of
photons on material actually exerts a
radiation pressure
so that is the momentum that photons
have but they are also
waves because they have a frequency and
wavelength and they part
and they travel across space across the
universe
in the vacuum of space they are
manifestations of this infinite field
the electromagnetic field
okay good question why can't we indians
make
jet engine technology if you can make
make a rocket engine
well it's a good question rocket engines
are more powerful but jet engines are
more complicated hang on
so we have been making rocket engines
since the 1970s at least
and yet we are trying to create a jet
engine the kaveri jet engine which is
being
under development for decades first of
all
the main reason the principal reason why
the cavalry jet engine
has not succeeded thus far is because of
political interference
when a foreign power gives a politician
a bribe and says buy my technology don't
develop your own technology
well certain kinds of politicians will
take that money and they will try and
delay the indigenous technology
development program
so one of the main reasons why the
indian technology
has been delayed thus far is because of
political interference that's why
the lca pages jet fighter was delayed
for so many decades
and in recent times it took off because
there was no more political interference
there was political will for this
program to come to fruition
and so that's one of the reasons why the
jet engine technology is
delayed the second thing is that it's a
very
difficult and complicated technology you
have to build uh
the jet engine turbine blades have to
withstand
enormous temperatures and pressures so
you basically have to build these jet
engine blades out of a single
crystal of metal so that technology
takes a long time to develop you need to
have a good
r d scientific ecosystem in the in the
country
in order to be able to develop the
technology and in
india well we don't have that sort of
ecosystem
the academic system is based upon rote
memorization
and teaching from textbooks it is not
based upon
research in the u.s the entire academic
system
is heavily based on research
in technology and so the same goes for
china
in india we don't have it the academic
system basically doesn't do any real
research
so these are some of the reasons why we
have not been able to develop the jet
engine technology thus far i hope that
changes i think there is political will
nowadays to some extent so i hope
it happens soon because we need that
okay let me take one more
question
let me take one more question if i can
find one
how long do you think until the human
brain can be reverse engineered and
uploaded to another substrate like
non-biological
intelligence i think it's very very far
from that stage
we don't understand the human brain we
don't understand how memory is stored
we don't understand how various patterns
are stored
so until we understand that adequately
we can't transfer memories or even
forget about consciousness we can't even
transfer memories properly
to another storage system
so the key is in understanding how the
brain works and how
memories are formed and what gives rise
to consciousness
only then can we upload it somewhere
else and
create a duplicate copy of that so that
is still very very far away
reverse engineering the human brain is
it's still
very much firmly in the realm of science
fiction
okay i get lots of questions lots of
questions about time travel what do i
think about time travel
tushar asks so i
think that from the understanding of
physics physics that we have thus far
it is most likely not possible
okay based on the understanding of the
laws of physics that we have thus far
there are many of these reports of time
travelers
coming from various from from the future
etc
and giving us some information etc well
it's never been confirmed
so one can think of it as an urban
legend none of it is confirmed right
but from the understanding of physics
that we have thus far
it appears that if trent if time travel
were possible it would basically
uh violate the causal structure of the
universe
so it appears that it is unlikely but
it's still something that we are
looking into we are still researching it
some solutions of the einstein equations
of general relativity may possibly
make wormholes possible traversable
wormholes
in which case time travel may
theoretically perhaps be possible
but maybe such wormholes can't be
traversed so it's going on it's a matter
of matter of
conjecture and debate and the last word
is not been spoken
about this yet but thus far it looks
like it most likely may not be possible
what is pokey action at a distance
shirish asks
it is quantum entanglement if you have a
pair of entangled particles
let's say one particle has spin up and
the other one has pinned down
they are entangled together in what is
known as quantum entanglement and they
are sent in opposite directions
in space and let's say after a few years
these two particles are one light year
apart
and let's say one particle is with me
and i it's in and i
take a look at it and i see it's spin up
then i will instantaneously know that
the other particle is pinned down
even though it is one light year away
from
where i am so it appears that this
information from the other particle
reaches me faster than the speed of
light so that is a very simplistic way
of looking at quantum entanglement
and that is what einstein called spooky
action at a distance
so it's one of the paradoxes of quantum
mechanics
it does seem to be faster than light
many times faster than light so it's one
of the mysteries of quantum mechanics
so that's what it is spooky action
at a distance okay my friends
uh this is the end of today's session
thank you so much for your questions
thank you for watching and i will see
you in the next
episode thank you so much have a good
night have a good day very
wherever you are bye